Guide to the Herbert Gans Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Writings, 1947-2004
  - Subseries I.1: Books, 1953-2003
    - Deciding What’s News: A Study of CBS Evening News, NBC Nightly News, Newsweek, and Time, 1979
      - Correspondence
        - Bullitt, Stimson, 1962-1971 (Box 64, Folder 6)
        - General, 1961-1963 (Box 16, Folder 9)
        - General, 1976-1980 (1 of 2 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 10)
        - General, 1976-1980 (1 of 2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Drafts
        - Manuscript--Early Version, 1971, (3 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 2 to 4)
        - Typescript--Before Copy Editing, 1979 (2 of 5 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 5 to 6)
        - Typescript--Before Copy Editing, 1979 (3 of 5 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 1 to 3)
        - Typescript--With Copy Editing, 1979 (3 of 5 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 4 to 6)
        - Typescript--With Copy Editing, 1979 (2 of 5 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Early Notes and Outlines, 1960s (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Grant Application, 1974-1975 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - NBC Letters, 1975-1976 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Opinion Pieces, 1979-1980 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Outline of Study, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - Project Descriptions, circa 1964-1965 (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Progress Reports, 1964-1968 (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Research Proposals, 1964-1971 and undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Reviews, 1979-1980 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Reviews, 1979-1980 (Box 64, Folder 7)
      - Talks and Speeches, circa 1979-1996 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Textbook Study, circa mid-1960s (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Middle American Individualism: The Future of Liberal Democracy, 1988
      - Correspondence, 1976-1988 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Notes and Memos, circa 1980s, (3 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 5 to 7)
      - Paperback Edition, 1988-1991 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - “Popular Individualism: An Essay on American Values and Politics,” 1986 (1 bound volume) (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Reviews, 1988-1989 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Typescript, 1988, (3 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 2 to 4)
    - The War Against the Poor: The Underclass and Antipoverty Policy, 1995
      - Correspondence with Foundations, 1989-1991 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Op-eds, Unpublished, circa 1990s (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Outlines and Study Proposals, circa 1988-1994 (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - Reviews, 1995-1996 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - Tables, circa 1990s (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - Talks, circa 1980s, 1990s (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Typescript, 1994, (3 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 2 to 4)
    - Making Sense of America, 1999
      - Typescript, 1999, (3 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 5 to 7)
    - Democracy and the News, 2003
      - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - Outlines, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - Outlines, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Typescript--with Edits, 2001, (2 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 2 to 3)
      - Typescript--Index of Names, circa 2002 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Typescript--Final Version, 2002 (1 bound volume) (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.2: Book-Length Studies, 1949-1969
    This subseries contains Gans's Masters and Doctoral theses and related materials, along with two studies carried out on the subject of television. Gans's M.A. thesis, "Political Participation and Apathy: A Study of Political Participation in Local Government and Some Recommendations to Increase Participation in the Government of Park Forest, Illinois" (1950), which he wrote at the University of Chicago, is accompanied here by drafts and preliminary studies, correspondence with academic advisers, and eight folders of interviews Gans carried out during his fieldwork in Park Forest. These files provide a valuable perspective on how Gans first grappled with the challenges of carrying out qualitative research based on in-depth fieldwork. Files related to Gans's PhD thesis, "Recreation Planning for Leisure Behavior: A Goal-Oriented Approach" (1957), include a 1960 revision of the dissertation, which Gans tried, in vain, to turn into a book.
    The two television studies — "American Films and Television Programs on British Screens: A Study of the Functions of American Popular Culture Abroad" (1959) and "The Uses of Television and Their Educational Implications: Preliminary Findings From a Survey of Adult and Adolescent New York Television Viewers" (1969) — are accompanied by correspondence and research materials. Together, they testify to Gans's longstanding interest in popular culture, especially film, and media.
    - M.A. Thesis [Many materials in this category are acidic and/or disintegrating.]
      - Correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - Drafts and Preliminary Studies, circa 1949-1950 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - Park Forest Interviews, late 1940s (1 of 8 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 8)
      - Park Forest Interviews, late 1940s (7 of 8 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 1 to 7)
      - “The Child-Oriented Jewish Community: A Study of a Suburban Jewish Sub-Community in Park Forest, Illinois,” 1955 (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - “The Jewish Community in Park Forest, Illinois: A Study in Jewish Community Formation,” 1950 (Box 25, Folder 2)
      - Thesis: “Political Participation and Apathy: A Study of Political Participation in Local Government and Some Recommendations to Increase Participation in the Government of Park Forest, Illinois” 1950 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Doctoral Thesis
      - Abstracts, 1956 (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 25, Folder 5)
      - Dissertation: “Recreation Planning for Leisure Behavior: A Goal-Oriented Approach,” 1957 (1 of 2 bound volumes) (Box 25, Folder 6)
      - Dissertation: “Recreation Planning for Leisure Behavior: A Goal-Oriented Approach,” 1957 (1 of 2 bound volumes) (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - “Recreation Planning for Leisure Behavior”--Unpublished Book Manuscript, 1960, (3 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 2 to 4)
    - “American Films and Television Programs on British Screens: A Study of the Functions of American Popular Culture Abroad,” 1959
      - Completed Study, 1959 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, 1957-1962 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Research Materials, late 1950s (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - Research Proposals, 1956-1957 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - “The Uses of Television and Their Educational Implications: Preliminary Findings From a Survey of Adult and Adolescent New York Television Viewers,” 1969, (2 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 4 to 5)
  - Subseries I.3: Articles, 1949-2004
    This subseries contains published and unpublished journal articles, magazine essays, short-form newspaper editorials, book reviews, film reviews, and lectures, along with related materials. Much of the organizing logic was provided by Gans, who created a list of 177 articles he authored between 1951 and 2004. This chronological list can be found in Box 29, Folder 1. It includes articles written for scholarly publications such as the Journal of the American Institute of Planners, Social Policy, and the American Journal of Sociology; for general-interest magazines such as The Nation, Commentary, and the New York Times Magazine; and as book chapters. Each article is numbered on the list and can be found under the corresponding number in subsequent folders; many articles also correspond to a numbered folder of related materials — correspondence, research files, clippings — either within this subseries or in Series II: Subject Files. Among the subject files, numbers within parentheses denote the article number to which the subject corresponds. For instance, the Series II folder labeled "1960s—City and Poverty (#48), 1965," corresponds to Article 48 on Gans's list, which is titled "The City and the Poor" and which can be found in Box 29, Folder 6.
    Absent from Gans's list are the bulk of his many newspaper articles; these are contained within four folders labeled "Unlisted Short articles." Also unlisted are book reviews Gans wrote for a variety of academic and mainstream publications, mostly in the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s, as well as the 30 film reviews he wrote in the 1970s for Social Policy. Finally, the subseries includes unpublished articles and talks, arranged in approximate chronological order (many are undated).
    - Article list--Compiled and Numbered by Gans (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Articles 1-40, 1951-1964, (4 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 7 to 10)
    - Articles 41-120, 1964-1981, (8 Folders) (Box 28, Folder 1 to 8)
    - Articles 121-177, 1981-2004, (6 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 1 to 6)
    - Related Materials
      - Article 4, 1951-1952 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - Article 8, 1949-1955, (3 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 8 to 10)
      - Article 12, 1958 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - Article 16, 1958-1959 (Box 30, Folder 2)
      - Articles 18, 21, 22, 1955-1961 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      - Articles 43-46, 1964-1965 (Box 30, Folder 4)
      - Article 66, 1968 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      - Article 67, 1965-1968 (Box 30, Folder 6)
      - Article 70, 1968 (Box 30, Folder 7)
      - Article 73, 1965-1968 (Box 30, Folder 8)
      - Article 75, 1969 (Box 30, Folder 9)
      - Article 81, 1969-1970 (Box 30, Folder 10)
      - Article 91, 1972 (Box 30, Folder 11)
      - Article 93, circa 1972-73 (Box 30, Folder 12)
      - Article 99, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 13)
      - Article 99, 1972-1974 (Box 30, Folder 14)
      - Article 102, 1973-1974 (Box 30, Folder 15)
      - Article 104, 1975 (Box 30, Folder 16)
      - Article 112, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 17)
      - Article 123, 1981 (Box 30, Folder 18)
      - Article 137, 1983-1989 (Box 30, Folder 19)
      - Article 141, 1989-1990 (Box 30, Folder 20)
      - Article 144, 1986-1992 (Box 30, Folder 21)
      - Article 145, 1990-1993 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - Article 149, 1990-1992 (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - Article 155, 1993-1994 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - Article 160, 1995 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - Article 163, 1995-1996 (Box 31, Folder 5)
      - Article 15, 1997-1999 (Box 31, Folder 6)
      - Article 169, 1999 (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - “Preserving Everyone’s Noo Yawk”, 1975 (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - “Should We Subsidize Popular Art?”, 1974-1975 (Box 31, Folder 9)
      - Various articles, 1974-1999 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Book Reviews, 1950s-1990s, (3 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 11 to 13)
    - Film Reviews, 1971-1978 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Unlisted Short Articles, 1960s-1990s (2 of 4 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 15 to 16)
    - Unlisted Short Articles, 1960s-1990s (2 of 4 Folders) (Box 32, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Unpublished Talks and Articles, 1950s-1990s, Undated (6 of 17 Folders) (Box 32, Folder 3 to 8)
    - Unpublished Talks and Articles, 1950s-1990s, Undated (7 of 17 Folders) (Box 33, Folder 1 to 7)
    - Unpublished Talks and Articles, 1950s-1990s, Undated (4 of 17 Folders) (Box 34, Folder 1 to 4)
  - Subseries I.4: Planning Documents, 1951-1988
    Gans's work in urban planning is documented here through writings, correspondence, and research materials. Much of this work dates from Gans's brief career as a professional planner during the 1950s; Gans also participated in the Forty-Second Street Development Project, which aimed to transform Manhattan's Times Square, and materials from that project are included here.
    - “A Comprehensive Planning Study of the Public Library,” 1955 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Anacostia-Bolling Urban Renewal Project, 1967 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Babbit, Minnesota, 1951, (2 Folders) (Box 34, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Babbit and Beaver Bay, Minnesota, 1951 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Cleveland, 1970s (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Columbia, Maryland, 1964-1973 (Box 64, Folder 8)
    - Forty-Second Street Development Project, 1984-1988 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - White Pine, Michigan, 1952 (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Subseries I.5: Other Writings, 1947-2003
    This subseries contains a miscellaneous assemblage of Gans's writings. Gans was an enthusiastic but rarely published satirist from his undergraduate years until the early 1970s, at which point he seems to have given up on the genre; collected here are published and unpublished satirical pieces, along with a number of rejection letters from such publications as The New Yorker and The Nation. Gans also fired off a steady stream of letters to the editor, many of which were published and are collected here. A frequent lecturer outside of his salaried teaching engagements, he amassed forty years worth of speaking notes that can be found in this subseries. The subseries also contains, among other writings, a 1965 essay titled "The Role of Housing in the War on Poverty," several unpublished children's stories from the 1970s, and two unpublished book-length compilations of Gans's essays.
    - Center for Urban Education--Memoranda and Studies, 1960s (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Children’s Stories--Unpublished, 1970s (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - “Entertainment and News”--Unpublished Gans Anthology, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 35, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Foreword to Easter Hill Village, 1969-1974 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - Letters to the Editor, 1960-2003, (2 Folders) (Box 35, Folder 10 to 11)
    - Satires, 1947-1971 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Speaking Notes
      - General, 1960-1999, Undated, (7 Folders) (Box 36, Folder 2 to 8)
      - News and Media, early 1970s (Box 36, Folder 9)
      - “The Future of the American City”, 1970s-1980s (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - “The Role of Housing in the War on Poverty, 1965 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Untitled Essay Collection, 1960s (Box 37, Folder 3)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1944-2004
  This series contains correspondence, news clippings, research notes, article drafts, policy papers, meeting minutes, and documents related to Gans's six decades a scholar, planner, teacher, writer, and activist. Explanatory notes written by Gans accompany several subject files.
  Some files are arranged chronologically by decade, which reflects their approximate order at the time of accession. Together, these files provide a snapshot of what Gans was doing at any given time at the peak of his activity in the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s. In 1968, for instance, he was thinking and writing about the interplay of culture and class, about the future of the suburbs, and about equality in America; he was testifying before the Kerner Commission and in an obscenity trial regarding a Swedish film; he was participating in the Society for the Study of Social Problems, the League for Industrial Democracy, Americans for Democratic Action, and the American Sociological Association. Other materials include the 1955 accusations of communist-related activities levied against Private Seymour Smidt, whose friendship with the allegedly leftist Gans was among the pieces of evidence wielded against him; research materials about Yiddish theater from the late 1940s and early 1950s; a 1967 letter signed by Robert F. Kennedy in response to Gans's inquiry about the Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; and materials pertaining to the infamous 1965 report on the black family authored by Gans's erstwhile friend, Daniel Patrick Moynihan. (Among these subject files, numbers within parentheses denote the article number to which the subject corresponds. For instance, the Series II folder labeled "1960s – City and Poverty (#48), 1965," corresponds to Article 48 on Gans's list, which is titled "The City and the Poor" and which can be found in Box 29, Folder 6.)
  Other material, some of which was labeled by Gans, is arranged alphabetically. Included here are materials related to the American Sociological Association, of which Gans was president in 1988; a draft manuscript of the influential book by Peter Marris (a friend of Gans's) and Martin Rein later titled "Dilemmas of Social Reform"; a transcript of Gans's testimony as an expert witness in the obscenity trial of Lenny Bruce; Gans's resumes and articles about Gans; material documenting Gans's lobbying efforts in behalf of dissident Hungarian sociologists imprisoned by that country's communist regime; drafts and correspondence related to a festschrift Gans edited about his friend and mentor, David Riesman; and notes, course readers, and syllabi from Gans's time as an undergraduate at the University of Chicago.
  - 1950s
    - Annenberg School, late 1950s (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Audience Image Paper (#9), 1956-1958 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Confidential Magazine Study, 1954-1956 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - “In Defense of American Sociology”--Unpublished, 1954-1960 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Journal of Informal Sociology (#15), 1957-1961 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Kibbutz Project, early 1950s (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Levenson, Sam, mid-1950s (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - Media Record, 1959 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Near West Side Planning Project, 1959 (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Popular Culture News, 1950s (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Research Notes and Memos, 1950s (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Saturday Evening Post Study 1957 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Smidt, Seymour--Allegations Against,1955 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Urban Planning, 1950s (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Yiddish Theater Research, 1940s-1950s (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - 1960s
    - American Sociological Association, 1967-1969 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Automation (#38), 1962-1964 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Beatles Piece (#44), 1964 (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation, 1967 (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - City and Poverty (#48), 1965 (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - Culture and Class, 1965-1968, (2 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 11 to 12)
    - Diversity (#19), 1961 (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - Education Planning, 1966 (Box 38, Folder 14)
    - Effects of Move (#35), 1962 (Box 38, Folder 15)
    - “Equality Revolution” (#71), 1968 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Federal Role in Urban Problems (#62), 1967 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Guggenheim Foundation Fellowship, 1968-1969 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Jacobs, Jane (#28), 1962 (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Kerner Commission, 1967-1969, (2 Folders) (Box 39, Folder 5 to 6)
    - League for Industrial Democracy, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - Moynihan Report (#47), 1965 (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - Neighborhood Viability, 1964-1965 (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - New York Housing Policy--Unpublished, 1961 (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - “Organization Man” data, 1960 (Box 39, Folder 11)
    - Outdoor Recreation (#30), 1959-1962 (Box 39, Folder 12)
    - Planning for People (#77), 1968 (Box 39, Folder 13)
    - Politics of Culture (#78), 1968 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Psychology Today Interview, 1969-1970 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Research notes, 1950s-1960s (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Reston New Town Study, 1963 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - Sherman, Allan (#34), 1958-1963 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Social Accounting (#63), 1967 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Social and Physical Planning (#33), 1962 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Society for the Study of Social Problems, 1967-1971 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Suburbs, Future of (#66), 1968 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - Television News (#79), 1969-1970 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - Testimony for “I Am Curious,” 1968 (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - Urban Crisis and Democracy (#76), 1969 (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - Urban Poverty and Social Planning (#60), 1962-1967 (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - Urban Renewal (#46), 1965 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Urbanism and Suburbanism as Ways of Life (#26), 1958-1962 (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - 1970s
    - Adult Learning and Public TV, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - “The American Architectural Experience,” 1975 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Australian and New Zealand Association for the Advancement of Science, 1979-1980 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Dolci, Danilo, 1972-1974 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Eastern Sociological Society, 1971-1973 (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - General, 1970s, (2 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 8 to 9)
    - Harris, Fred—Presidential Campaign, 1974-1976 (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Income Redistribution (#99), 1972 (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Joint Center for Urban Studies, 1969-1971 (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Packard, Vance (#94), 1972 (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - Social Science and Policy (#88), 1971 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Social Science Research Council, 1975 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Welfare (#86), 1971 (Box 64, Folder 9)
    - Young Presidents Association Paper (#92), 1971-1972 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Ad Hoc Council for New York Planning and Housing Policy, 1966 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Americans for Democratic Action
    - Equality Resolution, 1968 (Box 64, Folder 10)
    - Futures Project, 1972-1974 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - General, 1971-1977 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - American Sociological Association, 1973-2003 (4 of 6 Folders) (Box 42, Folder 7 to 10)
  - American Sociological Association, 1973-2003 (2 of 6 Folders) (Box 43, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Badillo, Herman, 1977 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Camp Avodah, 1944 (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Carnegie Commission on Higher Education, 1972 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Coalition for a Democratic Majority, 1972 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Columbia University Sociology Department, 1986-1989 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - “Community Action and the Professional Reformer: A Study of the Evolution of Community Action Projects,” by Peter Marriss and Martin Rein--Manuscript, circa 1966, (2 Folders) (Box 43, Folder 8 to 9)
  - Conflict with Rothman and Lichter, 1980s-1990s (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - Cultural Policy--National Endowment for the Humanities and Rockefeller Foundation, 1978-1979 (Box 43, Folder 11)
  - Ethnicity, 1970s (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Ethnicity--Second-Generation, 1991-1993 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Ethnicity--Symbolic, 1970s-1980s, (3 Folders) (Box 44, Folder 3 to 5)
  - Expert Witness, 1960s-1970s, 1982, (2 Folders) (Box 44, Folder 6 to 7)
  - Expert Witness--Trial of Lenny Bruce, 1964 (Box 64, Folder 11)
  - Faculty in Support of Columbia Students Who Refuse Military Service, undated (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation Income Maintenance Panel, 1967 (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Gannett Center for Media Studies, 1984-1997 (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Gans, Herbert--Resumes, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - Gans, Herbert--Writings About, 1962-2001 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - General Activities, 1980s-1990s, (3 Folders) (Box 45, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Hollywood Film Study, 1962 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Honors, 1982-1987 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Housing and Urban Development, Department of, 1977-1978 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Hungary
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - Research Trip, 1973 (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Szelenyi & Konrad, 1973-1975 (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Kemeny, 1974-1977 (Box 64, Folder 12)
  - I.F. Stone’s Biweekly-- Final Issue, 1971 (Box 45, Folder 10)
  - International Sociological Association, 1980-1981 (Box 45, Folder 11)
  - Judaism, 1940s-1950s (Box 45, Folder 12)
  - Moynihan, Daniel Patrick, 1972-1975 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - National Conference on Education and Inequality, 1974-1975 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - National Conference on the Distribution of Wealth, 1973 (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Nyden, Paul, 1974-1976 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Popular Culture, 1950s (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Poverty, Positive functions of, 1964-1994, (2 Folders) (Box 46, Folder 6 to 7)
  - Riesman, David--Festschrift, 1974-1979 (3 of 4 Folders) (Box 46, Folder 8 to 10)
  - Riesman, David--Festschrift, 1974-1979 (1 of 4 Folders) (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Socialism, 1950s-1960s (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Street Corner Society revisited--Correspondence with and about Marianne Boelen and William Whyte, 1971-1996 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Student Materials--University of Chicago
    - “Methods of Communication Research”--Notes and Essays, 1949 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - “Anthropology-Sociology 240”--Course Reader with Notes by Gans, 1948 (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - “Principles in the Sciences”--Course Reader with Notes by Gans, 1944 (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - “The Scope and Methods of Social Sciences”--Syllabus with Notes by Gans, 1946 (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - “The Media Sociology of Herbert Gans,” 1992-1994 (Box 47, Folder 8)